Chaim Gross Papers
Chaim Gross Papers
1937-1964
Gross, Chaim, 1904-1991.
1.75 linear ft.
Correspondence (1943-1964); and exhibition catalogs, clippings, and articles about Chaim Gross (1937-1964). Incoming correspondence includes that of Sidney Alexander, Associated American Artists, George Biddle, Theodore Bikel, Isabel Bishop, Butler Institute of American Art, Rhys Caparn, Federico Castellón, Philip Evergood, Robert Gwathmey, Benjamin Kopman, Leon Kroll, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Hedy Lamarr, Millard Lampell, Los Angeles County Museum of Art, Irving Marantz, Herman Maril, Museum of Modern Art, National Institute of Arts and Letters, New School for Social Research, Jan Peerce, Raphael Soyer, Sabina Teichman, Carl Van Vechten, Harold Weston, Whitney Museum of American Art, and William Zorach.
149023
Biographical History
Jewish American sculptor, 1904-1991.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1937 to 1964, the Chaim Gross papers comprises correspondence, artwork reproductions, writings and memorabilia of the American sculptor. With an emphasis on the early 1960s, the collection reflects Gross' later career and family life as well as his activities in the service of his Jewish community.
Incoming letters and related printed material constitute the Correspondence-Subject Files (Boxes 1-2), which forms the bulk of the collection. Although the collection contains few runs of correspondence, there are a number of social replies and a few business letters from fellow artists (George Biddle, Isabel Bishop, Henry Botkin, Federico Castellon, Anthony De Francisci, Philip Evergood, Estelle Goodman, Robert Gwathmey, Joseph Hirsch, Mary Mintz Koffler, Benjamin Kopman, Leon Kroll, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Bruno Lucchesi, William McVey, Irving Marantz, Herman Maril, Arnold Newman, Abbo Ostrowsky, Abbott Pattison, John Rewald, Raphael Soyer); authors (Sidney Alexander, Edward Halper, Arthur Kaufmann, Peter Pollack, Meyer Schapiro, Gilbert Seldes, Carl Van Vechten); and entertainers (Theodore Bikel, Dick Button, Hedy Lamarr, Jan Peerce). Organizational correspondence includes that of educational institutions (Brandeis University, Educational Alliance, New School for Social Research, Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture); galleries and museums (Art Institute of Chicago, Butler Institute of American Art, Carlebach Gallery, Brooklyn Museum, Jewish Museum, Los Angeles County Museum of Art, Museum of Art of Ogunquit, Museum of Modern Art, Shore Galleries, Whitney Museum of American Art); and professional affiliations (Association of American Artists, Committee of Artists' Societies, Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors, National Academy of Arts and Letters).
The remainder of the collection (Boxes 3-4) includes printed Artwork reproductions of some of Gross' drawings and sculpture; Writings, a single-page proposal for a sculpture project; and printed Memorabilia. The latter includes articles (1937-1963), clippings (1946-1964), and exhibit catalogs for Gross' one-person and group shows (1938-1964).
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Sculptors; Alexander, Sidney, 1912-1999.; Biddle, George, 1885-1973.; Bikel, Theodore.; Bishop, Isabel, 1902-1988.; Caparn, Rhys, 1909-1997.; Castellón, Federico.; Evergood, Philip, 1901-1973.; Gross, Chaim, 1904-1991.; Gwathmey, Robert, 1903-1988.; Kopman, Benjamin, 1887-; Kroll, Leon, 1884-1974.; Kuniyoshi, Yasuo, 1889-1953.; Lamarr, Hedy, 1913-2000.; Lampell, Millard, 1919-1997.; Manantz, Irving.; Maril, Herman.; Peerce, Jan, 1904-1984.; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987.; Teichman, Sabina.; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964.; Weston, Harold, 1894-1972.; Zorach, William, 1887-1966.; Associated American Artists.; Butler Institute of American Art.; Los Angeles County Museum of Art.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); National Institute of Arts and Letters (U.S.); New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997); Whitney Museum of American Art.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Austrian Americans.; Jewish artists -- United States.; Jews, American.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Artists.; Painters.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence-Subject files
  - A, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Sidney and Frances, 1964; undated (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, See National Institute of Arts and Letters.
  - American Friends of the Hebrew University, Inc., 1957-1964 (Box 1)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Artists Turn Toward Peace, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Associated American Artists, Inc., 1946-1964; undated (Box 1)
  - B, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Biddle, George, 1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Bikel, Theodore, 1961; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Bishop, Isabel, undated (Box 1)
  - B'nai B'rith, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Bocour, Leonard, 1962; undated (Box 1)
  - Botkin, Henry, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Brandeis University, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn Museum, 1951-1955 (Box 1)
  - Butler Institute of American Art (Youngstown, OH), 1958-1963; undated (Box 1)
  - Button, Dick, 1964 (Box 1)
  - C, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Caparn, Rhys, See Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors.
  - Carlebach Gallery (New York, NY), 1953-1963 (Box 1)
  - Castellon, Federico, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Caylor, George N., 1963 (Box 1)
  - Cole, Lilyan and Sylvan, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Committee of Artists' Societies (CAS), 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - D-F, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - De Francisci, Anthony, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Diamond, Freda, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Dyson, Katherine Warwick, See Butler Institute of American Art (Youngstown, OH).
  - Educational Alliance (New York, NY), 1953-1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Evergood, Philip, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors, 1963 (Box 1)
  - G, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Goodman, Estelle, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Goodrich, Lloyd, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Graham, John, 1948; undated (Box 1)
  - Gwathmey, Robert, 1954; 1959 (Box 1)
  - H, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Halper, Edward, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Halpert, Edith, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Hirsch, Joseph, 1964 (Box 1)
  - I-K, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Jewish Musem (New York, NY), 1953-1963 (Box 1)
  - Kaufmann, Arthur, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Koffler, Mary Mintz, 1943; undated (Box 1)
  - Kopman, Benjamin, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Kroll, Leon, 1955; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Kuniyoshi, Yasuo, 1948 (Box 1)
  - L, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Lamarr, Hedy, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Lampell, Millard, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1963-1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Lucchesi, Bruno, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Lyons, Leonard, 1959; 1964 (Box 1)
  - M, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - [Edward] MacDowell Association, Inc., 1953-1962 (Box 2)
  - McVey, William, 1940 (Box 2)
  - Marantz, Irving, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Maril, Herman, 1964; undated (Box 2)
  - Matson, Greta, undated (Box 2)
  - Meyerson, Bess, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Museum of Art of Ogunquit (Maine), 1954-1964 (Box 2)
  - Museum of Modern Art (New York, NY), 1951-1964 (Box 2)
  - N-O, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1954-1965 (Box 2)
  - New School of Social Research, 1954-1964; undated (Box 2)
  - New York Society for Ethical Culture, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Newman, Arnold, undated (Box 2)
  - Ostrowsky, Abbo, 1955 (Box 2)
  - P-Q, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Palley, George T., 1953; 1964,; undated (Box 2)
  - Pattisch, Abbott, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Peerce, Jan and Alice, 1964; undated (Box 2)
  - Philadelphia Art Alliance, 1956-1963 (Box 2)
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1943; 1949,; 1964 (Box 2)
  - Piccoli, Nemo, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Pollack, Peter, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Provincetown Art Association, 1964; undated (Box 2)
  - Provincetown Art Commission, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
  - R, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Rewald, John, 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - S, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Santa Barbara Museum of Art, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Schapiro, Meyer, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Seldes, Gilbert, undated (Box 2)
  - Shapiro, Saul, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
  - Shore Galleries (Boston, MA), 1954-1964 (Box 2)
  - Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture (Skowhegan, ME), 1954-1964 (Box 2)
  - Smithsonian Institution, 1961-1964 (Box 2)
  - Soyer, Ralph and Rebecca, 1953; 1964 (Box 2)
  - State of Israel Bonds, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
  - Strater, Henry, See Museum of Art of Ogunquit (Maine).
  - T-V, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Teichman, Sabrina, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Temple Emanuel Arts Festival (Newton Centre, MA), 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Tshacbasov, Nahum, 1954 (Box 2)
  - United Jewish Appeal of Greater New York, 1953-1964 (Box 2)
  - Untermeyer, Louis, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Van Veen, Stuyvesant, 1964; undated (Box 2)
  - W-Z, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - [Anna L.] Werbe Galleries (Detroit, MI), 1955-1963 (Box 2)
  - Weston, Harold, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1945-1964 (Box 2)
  - Zorach, William and Marguerite, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Zucker, Paul, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified (Box 2)
- Artwork
  - Reproduction (printed) of drawings and sculpture (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Proposal (Box 3)
- Memorabilia
  - Articles about, 1937-1963 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1946-1964; undated (Box 3)
  - Course catalogs, 1944-1964 (Box 3)
  - Exhibition catalogs
    - One-person shows, 1939-1964; undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Group shows, 1938-1959; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Group shows, 1960-1964; undated; 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Programs, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - Publicity, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellany (Box 4)